Guide to the Alexander Miller Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Alexander Miller papers
1930-1961
SC0495
Miller, Alexander, 1908-1960
1 Linear feet
These papers document a small portion of Miller's professional life. They consist primarily of manuscript and typescript articles, lectures, and essays; correspondence and records pertaining to his publications; and reprints, articles, and clippings of his published work. Other items include correspondence, biographical materials, and two photographs. The correspondent in the "Shadwell group" letters is W. G. Symons (who signs his letters "Christopher"); also included is a circular letter by Anne and Martyn Grubb. All of the letters pertain to ecumenical work among local communities in Great Britain and in the Student Christian Movement. The publishing correspondence includes several letters from Werner Koch, his German translator, that concern theological issues of the late 1940s; there are also letters pertaining to the Student Christian Movement in Europe.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Unpublished guide available.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Alexander Miller came to Stanford University in 1950 to inaugurate the curriculum in Religious Studies. He was ordained in the Presbyterian Church of New Zealand in 1937, and held pastorates there and in Scotland and England before coming to Stanford. From 1943 to 1945 he was associated with Sir George MacLeod in the Iona Community in Scotland. Throughout his career he was associated with the Student Christian Movement. He was the author of several books, including THE CHRISTIAN SIGNIFICANCE OF KARL MARX, FAITH AND LEARNING, and THE MAN IN THE MIRROR. In 1958 the Pacific School of Religion conferred upon him an honorary degree of Doctor of Divinity.
Description of the Collection
These papers document a small portion of Miller's professional life. They consist primarily of manuscript and typescript articles, lectures, and essays; correspondence and records pertaining to his publications; and reprints, articles, and clippings of his published work. Other items include correspondence, biographical materials, and two photographs. The correspondent in the "Shadwell group" letters is W. G. Symons (who signs his letters "Christopher"); also included is a circular letter by Anne and Martyn Grubb. All of the letters pertain to ecumenical work among local communities in Great Britain and in the Student Christian Movement. The publishing correspondence includes several letters from Werner Koch, his German translator, that concern theological issues of the late 1940s; there are also letters pertaining to the Student Christian Movement in Europe.
Access Terms
Grubb, Anne.; Grubb, Martyn.; Koch, Werner.; Miller, Alexander, writer on Christian sociology, 1908-1960.; Student Christian Movement of Great Britain and Ireland.; Symons, W. G.; Ecumenical movement --Great Britain.; religious studies; Students--Religious life.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Letters received, 1942-56 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, "Shadwell group," 1948-52 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Publishing correspondence and records (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publishing correspondence and records (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Approach to theology via society," 1948 (radio broadcast) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Introduction to Christian social ethics" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Life in the household of faith" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marxism/communism, essays on (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marxism and religion, essays on (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Meaning of work" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New Zealand and British politics, essays on (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Preaching in war-time" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Various articles and lectures (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book draft (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook of published work, 1930-42 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1936-44 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1945-50 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1947-55 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1957-61 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Galley (The community of faith in the community of learning) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reviews of Miller's books (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reviews of Miller's books (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Biographical material (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 2, Folder 11)